As I fast approach the ripe old age of
40, I've been doing something almost
obsessively for about a decade now that
helps retain what whispers of youth
still cling to my decrepit bones.
Am I being dramatic?
Yeah, leave me alone. While I'm not
afraid of aging, I would like to
maintain a youthful state for as long as
possible, as many others do, too. Maybe
that applies to you in some way or
another. Well, one of the most impactful
things that I do other than sustained
focus on exercise, nutrition, and sleep
is wearing sun protection, as in
sunscreen. Like I said, I'm pretty
obsessive about it. I wear it indoors.
In fact, I'm wearing it right now, which
only exacerbates the comments on my
pasty white complexion. I also wear it
in cold seasons. I reapply consistently
and more. The point being, it's a
long-term habit, and I ain't trying to
kick it. So, why the focus on sun
protection? And is there any risk to
such focus on sunscreen considering that
there's rumors that it leeches through
the skin? Well, let me present two
arguments for why the focus on
sunscreen. One, the direct anti-aging
benefits. An isolated example is what I
actually have for the thumbnail of this
video here. This woman put on sunscreen
for 40 years on her face, but not on her
neck, and she's 28 years old. Well,
ignore the fact that that math doesn't
math. I'm just hoping that you're just
as bad at it as I am. No, in earnest,
she's in her 90s in this image, and it's
clear the massive impact that sunscreen
has. Still, we shouldn't focus on a
single image. As impactful as it is,
let's discuss the science. If you look
at the literature on sunscreen, there's
multiple intervention trials that show
consistently that sunscreen has
anti-aging properties. For example, this
one where researchers measured before
and after one year of sunscreen use in
30 individuals. You can see the
different assessments on the horizontal
axis and each bar corresponding to a
length of time of daily sunscreen use.
And if the bars go up, that's deemed
clinically improved skin. Across the
board, sunscreen use leads to
improvements regardless of the measure
used. Now, some of these studies are
poorly controlled, like the data that I
just showed you, as there's no blinding
or control group. However, there are
other studies that fill in some of those
issues with rigor, like using placebo
creams that look identical, but don't
contain sunscreen ingredients, and they
show similar results. I'd like to pause
here and point out that people are aging
because time is going by. But the
sunscreen isn't just slowing the aging,
it's stopping or reversing it. As before
and after is often the same or improved
from baseline. In fact, in other
studies, the researchers say that daily
sunscreen use shows, and I quote, no
detectable increase in skin aging after
4.5 years. We're talking about a
stoppage of skin aging. Now, while I'd
love to leave it there, the reality is
that while almost five years is a long
time to freeze aging, I would guess that
given enough time, aging would still
march forward even through a sunscreen
slathered resistance. That's because
sunscreen protects against exttrinsic
aging. the UV radiation that's
penetrating our skin, entering the
cells, and damaging the proteins, other
molecules, and genes of our skin cells
causing mutations. However, sunscreen
can't protect us against inherent
imperfections of biology, meaning the
intrinsic factors like oxidative stress
that occurs from, well, simply living.
But regardless, we're taking several
years of protection, if that's through
evidence of slowing aging, stopping it,
or reversing it. The point being that
sunscreen is an incredibly powerful tool
in combating skin aging. However, some
people don't care as much about skin
benefits from an aesthetic perspective,
but they may care more from reason
number two, surviving to a ripe old age.
While we may be focused on injections,
supplements, and whatever else that we
can squeeze out additional few months or
years out of our body, the greatest
impact on our longevity is your mere
survival to a relatively advanced age
for all those other factors to even
matter. If you die at 34, supplements
and special protocols don't do much
good. So, what's one of the leading
causes of premature death?
Cancer. It might seem obvious, though
there are some health influencers that
say things like this,
>> right? Um [music]
um expose your skin to sunlight. Sun's
not our enemy. The fact is most of us
are not getting enough sun when it's not
that we're getting too much sun. If you
look at um the number of of commercial
sunscreens, I think there's 23 of them
that have been pulled from the market
since 2018 for directly causing cancer.
>> Wow. [music] Um and if you actually were
to overlay a chart, maybe I'll send you
this chart so you can throw it on throw
it on the podcast. Um, if you were to
overlay a chart of the incidence of the
increased use of sunscreen and the rapid
rise of skin cancer, you know, you would
just see this oxymoronic
message that says, well, if if we're
using sunscreen at 45 times or 50 times
the rate that we were in 1980, shouldn't
we have less skin cancer?
>> Yeah.
>> Well, why is it that we have more skin
cancer? Um, and we're actually getting
less sun and applying more sunscreen.
It's because the whole script's been
flipped. You know, we think that we we
need chemicals and synthetics and
pharmaceuticals to thrive. We don't. We
need minerals, amino acids, nutrients to
thrive.
>> I'm not going to go off debunking every
aspect of this, though there's a lot
wrong with it. But we can focus in on a
prevalent piece. Sunscreen causes skin
cancer.
We can test that directly because we
have randomized control trials that test
what happens when people are told to put
on sunscreen every day compared to only
occasionally. And two types of skin
cancer prevalence were tested over 4 and
1/2 years. In the end, one skin cancer
was unaffected by sunscreen use and the
other was significantly reduced. And
when followed for longer over 15 years,
about 10 to 11 years after the trial
ended, we can see here there's a
continued protection. The higher the
lines, the more melanoma, so skin
cancer. The blue line is the people
using sunscreen for those almost 5
years. So the direct intervention data
indicate that no, sunscreen does not
cause skin cancer, but actually protects
against it. This is critical because it
then increases the odds of living
longer, i.e. an indirect longevity
effect. I'd also add on the sunscreen
front, most studies use pretty low
thresholds for sunscreen. So, we're t
talking something like SPF 15, maybe SPF
30. So, the lower end of the protection,
but still quite potent in results. But
of course, there are rumors that
sunscreen ingredients can also leech
into your blood. Are those rumors true?
Yes, they are. Now, before I go on, I'm
covering the impact that beta carotene
has on skin aging and skin cancer along
with if age, skin complexion, type of
work outdoor and indoor move the needle
meaningfully in my extended analysis of
this video that you're currently
watching. If you're interested, you can
join the Physionic Insiders, my premium
research platform that I developed to
access this full analysis, plus hundreds
of others in video and written article
format, plus quick summaries, a regular
monthly podcast, live sessions with me,
and more. Check it out. The link to join
the Physionic Insiders is in the
description box. I hope to see you
there. There are multiple studies that
look at sunscreen and more specifically
sunscreen ingredients like avoenzone,
oxyenzone and the like and show that
there are detectable levels in the blood
when applied to our skin. The question
then is is this harmful to our health?
Well, we do know that there's some
temporary changes in hormones, but these
changes don't last long and are actually
quite minor. I wish I could tell you
that we have strong evidence debunking
any potential harm and we do have some
longerterm studies on the relationship
to hard end points like death showing
sunscreen does not raise the risk of
death. But as you know, there's a lot
between something being healthy and
something killing you. Unfortunately, we
don't have a ton of data directly
indicating sunscreen safety across all
possible outcomes. Just to be clear,
this does not mean that sunscreen is
unsafe either. We need more data on
sunscreen directly, but what we also
know is what molecules get into our
bloodstream are in tiny amounts and are
generally recognized as unlikely to
cause lasting problems at such small
concentrations. In the end, making a
riskbenefit analysis, the benefits of
sunscreen outweigh the negatives, at
least for me. Of course, it also depends
on the type of sunscreen. So, chemical
versus mineral-based, for example, as
mineral-based are less likely to be
absorbed. Ultimately, I've chosen to
stay the root of liberal sunscreen while
understanding that we don't know
everything about it. That's a personal
decision, but that does not mean that
you have to do the same. Plus, since I
hear the howls of sun lovers descending
upon me like a hawk to fish, I'm also
not saying that the sun is unhealthy for
you or that you should avoid it. I
don't, though my complexion may beg to
differ. But I am saying that some
protection for the skin is beneficial if
that's sunscreen or simply shade or
clothing or what have you. Speaking to
skin aging, remember when I mentioned
sunscreen doesn't address intrinsic
aspects of skin aging? Well, I cover
something that tackles that and improves
skin health right here. Thanks for
tuning in. I'm going to go apply some
more sunscreen. See you in the next one.